find how should [music] we clone what is
already in the market or you uh like so
that is [music] the build part or you
just latch on on something which is
already there and build on that. [music]
So why and this is a build versus buy
decision is very difficult to fail uh
not because LL is that it is because
[music] people are not ready to adopt it
for multiple reason like uh it is not
[music] in the flow. It is not easy for
them to use it.
Sometimes it is just the status quo.
They're very comfortable in their
advance.
I have a treat for you all. uh been on
location here at Plenty Florida
Hollywood in Las Vegas for the put data
first conference. We are having a blast
and today I'm really excited to be
joined by Ritu. Uh welcome to the signal
room.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for agreeing to just
sit down and and have a conversation. I
think it's been remarkable how much
passion and enthusiasm we're running
into in this room over the last couple
days and getting to meet you has been
wonderful and meeting so many different
people. It just seems like we're at a
really different point cuz when you're
at the beginnings of a transformation of
any kind, people tend to be a little
tentative and kind of laidback kind of
waiting to see how this is going to play
out, but everyone's leaning in and
they're so excited. I So just maybe just
to start with, just tell me a little bit
about your background. I mean, I know
you're doing AI strategy and, you know,
pretty cool stuff, but I don't think
I've seen you without a smile on your
face since since I saw you yesterday for
the first time. So you clearly you're
passionate about what you're doing. Love
to understand what's behind all that.
And
absolutely. First of all, thank you so
much for having me here. Uh I am glad
that I could make it. Uh I was kind of a
skeptical that should I be going it like
taking two days off Monday to Wednesday
uh is tough
but I think I made a right decision and
should be here. uh there was so much in
the room and in terms of energy
to learn that like uh from each other uh
with how things are happening but
starting with my background so I'm in
this industry I would say uh almost two
decade so very long my degree I would
say of I'm an engineer and uh first
taste of ITI I would say was my my
research which I did the in neural
network and during that time it was very
specific use cases. So how do you do the
digital signal processing?
That was my PhD paper uh in my
engineering
and then uh that was also a time when
software was taking shape. Right. So
started my career as an analyst and from
there uh uh I would say AI it is like
almost 12 years uh during the time like
I left that neural uh
right
engine and that uh neural processing but
then uh came big data and that was just
a talk of the down since then I was part
of uh exit strategy in consulting and
applied intelligence did my startup for
a while and then I realized that okay I
should be enterprise doing something
more a generative AI space. So now for
commercial I'm on AI product strategy
putting together the AI product which is
sim our commercial
that's exciting how are you finding it
the challenge that I've I've been
running into cuz I've been on the chief
data officer side in the healthcare
sector there are so many solutions
coming at us from every direction
generally they they addressing a really
small part of a very large gap that we
try to fill and the difficulties with
that are primarily financial ones
because you can't afford to have 10
things to fill one gap, right? And then
sometimes it's not even the right gap
that we're trying to fill. So it's
complicated, but you know, in your your
job, what what you have to think about
is that not only is it the right
solution, but strategically when do you
do certain things and when is it going
to be meaningful, when is adoption going
to be a problem, when is it a risk and a
compliance issue? There's so many other
so many things that go into what you're
responsible for. I just love to hear
what your approach is.
Right. Absolutely. And as you said, uh
there's so many solutions. So every day
you see face sample and then you wake up
and you find another taxion in the back.
So um for a person like me who is
responsible for putting together what
the product strategy looks like finding
out should we clone what is already in
the market or
you uh like so that is the build part or
you just
latch on on something which is already
there and build on that. So my uh and
and this is a build versus buy decision
is very difficult
right
the way I approach is the starting from
the end
what we are trying to achieve where is
the value lies and it's very easy like
looks like very complex but looking from
that okay where where it is going to
increase our revenue where it is going
to give us a cost starting from that
angle then going like a double take a
dip and say okay which are the areas
where you can have these values quickly
achievable. So that low hanging fruit
and then again that I I applied litmus
test for that very simple letm test
anything where AI could help us before
even finding that which is the right
solution first of all is it a AI
solution or
so it comes to
like do I have a digital like so that
this information is digital or not can I
verify
if I can ver because if you can't trust
it you can't use it you can't adopt this
is the my first test for adoption so
Once I have that like a very quick list
must test on the viability as well as
the physibility side and without
involving too many people then it comes
to bringing the right
because what I say that it's always the
case product fail not because um LLM
core the model is bad it is because
people are not ready to adopt it for
multiple reason they are like a it is
not in the flow it is not easy for them
to use it sometimes it is just the
status quo they very comfortable in
their environment.
So that bringing them uh in a like a mix
from the beginning.
So my question is I I use a very uh
quick uh framework Stop, Easy, Flow
zero. So basically if I bring this
product what are the three things you're
going to stop at tomorrow. So that
helped me to bring them in this mix and
the adoption property
and then during the design you design
the product in such a way it is in flow.
So it's not another point to solution.
So for example if I'm doing working on a
like a um
analyzing some information right
and I'm in a rush
I don't want to go into another chat box
and identify okay what's happening in
the data. I want to know that okay a
here is the 3% why it is happening can I
do something about it right
so can I have a conversation about it
and that's where it is easy to similar
if um I'm working in my share point and
I have lot my content I want to know
that okay in last one month
right
what are the different things happening
can I have a summary and just set it to
my boss right so I need to have that my
chat or my conversation right there
right
yes
so that's the flow and then the easy
part is like is it easy for me to
navigate
or do I need to do a three four steps
enable certain things and then only I
can use my product. So these are the
three things on the product designing
side which is like I'm working with the
technical
and that's where it actually helped me
to not only bring a product which is
useful
but people want to use it and so I think
that's I
you're seeing AI getting the same kind
of interest and reactions that
what dashboards were at one point in
time and it was amazing when when we
first started deploying them and my
first experience Since the very first
one, it just caught on. People got
excited and all of a sudden they had
dashboard envy. You happen to have a
very wellthoughtout problem that you
wanted to solve. The dashboard seemed to
be the right thing. We work with you.
You launch it. One of your colleagues
sees it. They're like, "Well, I want
one." And they call me telling me they
want a dashboard. And my team is going
through. It's like this. They really
just need a a list. But then the the
worst part is the overengineering. These
people that design some of the
solutions, I mean, the incredibly
brilliant people. and what motivates
them or makes them tick is creating
something that's really really useful
and it's powerful but they can get
really excited and over overgineer it
and I'm not nearly as technical as most
but I have tended to overengineer some
things myself but the problem is if it's
not explainable it's like a comedian
telling a joke that no one understands
the punch line they're asking a question
if if it's not self-evident you didn't
do it right if you're not answering the
the the very first question that someone
needs to have it answered like you
brought up a great point is it going to
enable a better decision to get made
what you're showing me change any
decision that I could make at all
improving my agency right
helping me to do something better so and
that's where it it actually helps
because easiness
it's in flow I'm not taking three extra
step because as long as if you ask
people to do xyz more they say I'm
already overloaded I already have so in
my plate and you are asking me to use
your product.
I have to do three steps. No, thank you
so much. I am going to use the same
thing what I'm doing here.
So yeah,
you know it's interesting the quick
reaction sometimes is because everyone's
excited is they want to come up with a
new solution. But one of the most
glaring solutions that I saw in in the
last few years was at my doctor's
office. And what they were doing that I'
not seen people doing well was so
simple. I'm walking out the door to the
waiting room and she made the
appointment for me right then and there.
It took her 10 seconds and she handed me
a a business card with the the schedule
on it. Gaps in care is a real problem in
healthcare because the basics of
clinical protocol are not pushed down to
the levels they should be. So the
physician knows when he needs to see the
patient, but he's not he doesn't do the
scheduling, don't probably even have
access to touch the schedule. But it was
really as simple as in that particular
practice in that specialty, the kind of
patients that they see there, the
clinicians made sure that the the front
desk people who are interacting with the
patients, they knew what the standards
were
and they took care of it in a piece of
paper is something that people are
trying to solve with a whole bunch of
technology now,
right?
But the right solution is is sometimes
the really it's an easy one.
I always say that just because AI is a
shiny tool,
right?
Not necessary. that is not a AI
solution. So do Should or Could test
should I be using the AI or
and then comes two could I do it right
my so that's where the litmus test is
first is the viability about that should
and that could is like okay do I have a
digital information is it
and al like if it is very easy for human
to do like you gave examplex
and then put it into until I see that
future usage or I want to scale left so
that it could be extended. So yeah,
these are the decision as a product
strategy.
Well, but the good news is that people
that are really smart and can do those
things, they have you. So you keep them
grounded and they slow down. I know you
like to use your hammer, but we can
actually use a piece piece of tape on
that. It's really not that important.
Absolutely. And that's exactly what
happens because sometimes you don't need
a full weight dissolution. need uh and
and that's where and you rightly said
this is such an important discussion
because many times especially if you're
working with a tech team to build a lot
of things
they're great at it. Here's the idea.
They say, "Oh, let's make a way. Let's
have 120 m then let's build it." And
then my question is, wait a minute.
Within our uh kitchen, you may have
certain tools which you can immediately
start using it and at least have a 30%
benefit. Right?
So, so uh can we use that and then see
the value adoption? Are people using it?
That is a signal. People are coming back
to your solution even if it is half
paid. Then you know that they like it
and then you want to make it better
better.
So like just first of all finding that
do they want to go from point A to point
B. So have that cycle and then make
Ferraris or to see that that like they
are taking that father.
The interesting dynamics they tend to be
cultural in a lot of ways. We've talked
about this in so many different contexts
over the last couple days, but human
trust is is is kind of a big deal. Um
there's fear involved. People are afraid
it's coming for my job. When you're
you're working with with teams and
identifying the the the workflows that
you're going to go after. Often times
there's the experience has been that oh
here they come. They're going to ask me
to do something else that's going to
change my workflow. And to your point,
it's not inflow. And that's something
that you look at. What are some things
that you you're dealing with trying to
actually counter what those experiences
have been in order to get them to be
comfortable and willing to trust that
you know what she's not coming for my
job. She's she's trying to help me to
become more valuable and work on more
higher priorities. This is such an
important thing and I think everyone
whoever is in like our uh shoe need to
think about because um so when we when I
say that like an easy framework for stop
easy and flow uh the most important
thing is then come start. So you're
stopping something what are you
starting? So rather than asking that
what are you going to start is my
question is what it is going to enable
you to do
if you want to do it today but you are
not and as soon as you say that that's
where you are catching on their trust
because now they know that okay sis the
tool is coming help me to be a better
version of myself
like improve my uh not the product I
would say improving my decision
right
capability so that's where the you
actually latch on and say your job is
not going anywhere rather you are
opening yourself for the better thing
and I like the way uh so I was reading
about it and when
most of the job would be gone with uh
new tools that are coming with the
physical AI
right
and that jobs are something that you do
not want to do
that's right
if it is a dirty and difficult job from
we are taking away from
Yes,
that's nearly at fear
because I don't want to go into a ditch
and find out like or like do some kind
of repair. That's difficult. I don't
like to do it.
But if somebody can do it and I will
just operate from like while sitting on
my desk and then
remove move the robot and that's and a
robot can do.
That's what I would love to do. I'm not
losing my job but I'm getting a better
which will help me not to put myself
under
right you know it's interesting working
around data data analysts data
architects ETL developers for a number
of years one of the things that I've
observed I'm sure you've seen it too
analysts spend
easily 60 to 70% of their time
wrangling the data getting it fit for
use very little time doing actual
analysis and when you actually can
automate the things and They're they're
a little nervous about it to begin with
because, you know, they're they see
their value in a different way. So, I
I've always had to coach my teams,
you're not here because you can do stuff
with technology,
right?
And because you know all the technology,
you're here because you're able to
figure out what's the right solution to
the problem that we're trying to solve.
And it's what you what's in your head,
what you know, and how you think, how
you approach things, how you network
with people. That that's the stuff that
really is valuable. But if you're like
talk to very very effective to to
actually start to repair some of and
restore some trust with the people to
your point they're fearful from losing
their jobs. Right.
Also I would say um the most important
thing is fear. So the fear is when you
don't know.
Yes.
When you don't know what is coming and
why it is coming.
So start with
educating your people. So that's why AI
literacy is super super critical
and it has to be sponsored from the top
right
like why as long as human are able to
know that why it is what it is
then they they will find their own path
but if they don't know then they will
speculate that's right
because even for a good AI to work needs
as you said that you are here for a
reason because that this data works what
way right so You have institutions of
knowledge, you have that uh kind of a I
would say the recipe that how people
Yes.
So
like
going
right
and as long as people understand that
that's where they will start leaning in
that's where they will start adopting
it. So then then your whatever you see
the barrier it's slowly slowly losing up
and that's where um start with literacy
making it uh uh like from the top side.
So for example you record video with
Kang and then you share with your team
saying that okay I'm super excited I got
this tool I recorded this video and this
has helped me to do the thing which I
used to take a five takes now it has
done what take me what's your feedback
now people know that oh my CEO is using
it
to use it and why don't I use it so my
CEO is not afraid but my dealer is not
afraid
so that's where like uh you show them,
inspire them, educate them.
I love that.
And help them to
I love that cuz I think that the reality
is there's a lot of people inside of
large organizations that are taking it
upon themselves cuz they're seeing
enough, you know, whether it's through
friends, family, colleagues, they're
experimenting, they're learning stuff
already. So, you know, not only is it
important for the CEO or the executive
team to be aware of it and learning
things for themselves, they also need to
understand that their teams are already
doing it. They don't have they may not
be doing it on their job. They may be I
I don't know the answer to that,
but there are a lot of people that are
actually learning it. And I think the
mistake that we can make is really not
delving into it. Sadly, and and this is
something I'm I'm glad we're here to
you're the right person to talk about.
For a CEO, their peer group, a very high
functioning people, they're very
successful. Some of them may have a
really great strategist that they lean
on a lot. Some of them may not. And what
are the one of the things that I'm
really concerned about now is if there's
a CEO out there that doesn't have access
to a strategist, how on earth are they
going to navigate? Because it's human
nature. I can talk about buzzwords. I
know what you're talking about to a
certain extent, but I might not have
enough understanding to know what are
the steps I can take in in the near term
and [snorts] how do I avoid looking like
I don't know anything, right? People
need a trusted advisor, right? Maybe
talk a little bit about that. What what
should somebody be looking for? You
know, what's a CEO really going to
benefit from and what's so important
about the work that you do? I mean, I
understand it. Um but tell the CEOs out
there how you can help them and what
they should be looking for
and I so it's super basic and it it is
not starting from AI as a senior you
must understand where your strength lies
where are the gaps right or in in that
way in any leadership role so
understanding that what I know what I
don't know and then we used to call it
like in back in the days jar's window
that what you don't know what you others
so do some kind of a strategic framework
like could collapse and all that. So
understand your operating framework.
Self awareness is the critical one. Once
you understand that like what is my role
and responsibility and what I bring on
the team now you need to know that in
order for me to fulfill my role and
responsibility here is the gap
and ultimately we are humans accepting
that with the self awareness that here
is the gap that gap
shy away. So bring those people whether
like a partner with the uh like
consulting firm or have somebody on your
like back okay as a strategist
right
nowadays AI tools are also helping you
to at least
yes
have a kind of a starting point
uh find out that okay what these uh
these uh like basic question at least
little awareness so self you can
selfucate yourself as well but again
having said that like you may have the
superficiary level information but in
order to like you are a CEO right so and
you have a stakeholder uh responsibility
so understanding that gap and cing I
would say that every CEO should have AI
advisor directly reporting to them
yes I agree
and if you don't have you are if you are
going by a path of co all
I think that's a mistake
no I agree with
because if you have a AI strategist who
has a a great knowledge about the
subject and and then have spent good
time again I would say that this AI
advisor should also be a mix of
technology plus business because
somebody who just knows technology does
not handle business cannot be a good
advice
thank you for saying that
choice of somebody who has that deliver
uh outcomes in a business That's right.
And they now have a strong knowledge of
AI subject. They should be our
best technical people are going to have
a bias towards doing technical things.
Absolutely. You
say and we want them to do that but we
have to have the two things coming
together and it it is a unique person
that actually can see those things and
figure out how to marry them and how
they should collaborate and work
together. I'm there is a firm called uh
thought and they have coined it a
generalist.
That's the which is like generalist who
have seen a different uh facet of
business
right
have a business degree of business
delivered outcome your revenue and top
and down values and then you they are
very good understanding of technology
that's the best combination you give
I totally agree with you as we're
wrapping up if people want to get in
touch with you how how do they find you
yeah best way LinkedIn so and it is very
simple my first name, last name, you can
find it.
Beautiful. And for those of you
listening, we will definitely put her
information in the show notes. It's been
amazing to be able to sit down and talk
with her. I really appreciate you taking
the time and viewing with me. I'm
excited. We we've got so much great
content that we've come come out of
these meetings with and we still got
some more to go. But I I look forward to
staying in touch with you and I can't
wait to have you on again. I'm sure
there'll be plenty of new late breaking
news the next time we talk. So again,
thank you so much for taking the time.
Thanks for being on
and it was a pleasure talking to you.
Thank you.